I will ask the world's smartest
model, GPT 5.5, what is the weather
right now in Hyderabad via API,
and it responds, I don't have the
access to live weather data in this
chart, so I cannot tell the exact
weather right now.
But what do we all know?
Chart GPT, Gemini, Cloud,
these are the powerful brains which
are called LLMs that can do any
single thing.
If we ask a simple weather,
what would it be? Why?
Because all of these LLMs are like
super powerful brains but are
trapped inside a jar guys.
They don't have hands and legs to do
the task.
So what we are going to do in this
video is, let's see how we can give
hands and legs which are also called
tools to these LLMs such that they
can take actions on behalf of us.
And this is the core foundation of
building your autonomous agents from
scratch guys.
Before we build our final agent,
let's understand the difference
between a chart bot and an agent.
So what do you usually do?
You have your questions.
For these questions, you will ask to
an LLM, it could be Chart GPT,
Cloud, Gemini, and LLM will give you
the answers based on its technology
and knowledge.
Very simple, isn't it?
This is how an LLM usually works and
this is our brain that we are
talking about.
But what if I want to book
tickets from Rajahmundry to
Hyderabad via flights?
Do you think a normal LLM can do all
of these things?
No. But what if you need to provide
the same question to an agent?
What will happen then?
By looking at this question,
using the same LLM as the brain,
it will decide that I need to book
flights from Rajahmundry to
Hyderabad.
I need to first do a web search
and once it finalizes the flights,
it needs to book the tickets
via Make
My Trip.
Now, these are what we call as
tools. Once these tools are
executed, whatever the output that
you get, this output will be sent
directly back to the LLM,
the brain, based on the tool
executions.
And then this LLM will look at all
of these outputs and it will give
you the final output as an LLM
answer.
What are you doing here?
The same question, you are routing
it through an agent. This agent,
based upon its knowledge,
initially it will decide that I need
to do a web search and book tickets
via MMT and if it has access to
these two tools,
let's say these two tools are
executed and the output is sent back
to the LLM, and then this final
LLM will give you the final answer
based on this agent, what it does.
This is what an agent is.
Isn't it? So, what if I want this
agent to connect to my database?
I can do it. What if I want this
agent to maybe make payments on
behalf of me?
I can do it. If I can give you
access to the bank account and what
if I want this agent to connect to
my calendar? I can do this.
So, this is what agents is.
Agents are nothing too complex,
guys. The same LLMs that we have,
ChatGPT, Claude, Gemini,
Croc, but with a simple tool
execution. That is what an agent is.
So, what we are going to do in this
video is, we will see how to build a
basic agent from scratch to the end
just like a production engineer will
do.
Simple, but Balaji, if I go to
ChatGPT and click on,
let's say, web search and I say,
check flights from Hyderabad to
Rajahmundry for today.
So, if you see, it will give me the
results by doing the web search and
it will give me the ticket details
as well.
And why is that happening?
Because this ChatGPT UI has all
the tools that are built by the
OpenAI developers.
Here, you are not using the raw
ChatGPT API that we are looking
here, rather than you are looking at
the ChatGPT, which has been built
by the developers of OpenAI by
providing all of these tool access,
guys.
If you don't have these tool access,
ChatGPT will just be a dumb model
and it cannot take actions on behalf
of you.
And there are so many tools that you
can connect. Let's say,
see, thinking and then create image,
web search, study and learn,
agent mode.
These are all the tools that have
been created for you. But in
production, you are going to
communicate with ChatGPT via API,
right?
So, who is going to build all of
these tools?
We are the one that needs to build
all of these tools such that our
application will be as powerful as
ChatGPT, if not more personalized,
that can connect to our databases,
that can do our personal things.
That is the goal of this video.
Now, we are going to build our
custom agent from scratch.
I have created notebook to
demonstrate every single thing.
And I will put the link in the
description below to get the same
exact notebook.
You can go ahead and download and
make a copy of it.
So, what are we doing here?
First, we are going to install the
OpenAI package because we are going
to use OpenAI API.
And you can install this.
And after that, we are going to
import this package called OpenAI.
Let's import this.
And then we are going to use two API
keys.
One is OpenAI API key and Groq API
key.
If you don't have OpenAI API key,
you can use Groq.
That is why I am showcasing both of
them.
You can use whatever you are
comfortable with.
So, in my environment file,
I have both of my API keys.
I can execute this piece of code by
saying OpenAI API key and Groq API
key.
And I can load both of my API keys.
If you are using Google Collab,
you can use it from this piece as
well.
So, it is up to you.
Right now, I am using cursor as an
IDE.
So, it is completely up to you where
you want to execute your code.
And what should we do after that?
We need to initialize our clients.
So, using OpenAI API key,
I am going to initialize my OpenAI
client.
And using Groq API key,
using the base URL, I am going to
initialize my Groq client as well.
We can change these two clients
alternatively whenever we are
calling LLMs.
So, what should we do first?
We will call our first LLM based on
the question, what is the weather in
Hyderabad right now?
How should we do this?
So, what should we say in our prompt
engine?
First, we need to put what is the
persona of the LLM.
For that, what are we doing?
You are an helpful assistant.
Use tools when needed.
It is basically the persona.
And after that, I need to create a
role, which is what we call a
system.
And what is the content in that?
The persona that we are creating.
And after that, we are creating one
more dictionary, the role,
user and JP.
What is the content in this?
This is the question that we want to
ask to an LLM.
And then we are going to ask to the
most powerful model, GPT 5.5.
And let's try and execute and see
the output.
And the output is going to be,
it doesn't know the answer.
Look at this one.
I don't have access to the live
weather data.
Simple. We know this already.
And that is what we are going to
solve right now.
And I can put the output in a pretty
format as well.
You can look at it later on.
What I am going to do is,
I am going to put it to Llama 3.3 70
billion parameter model.
This is also the top tier model
right now, which are available from
Llama models.
And look here.
I am a large language model.
I don't have access to the real time
weather data.
Even this doesn't have that kind of
capabilities.
So what do we need to do?
We need to write the tools to get
that kind of output.
So without directly calling the
weather API, I will explain it using
a very simple function.
How to create tools.
And using those tools,
how you can create agents.
And then you can incorporate that
learning to make better agents.
So what we are going to do is,
first let's write two basic
functions.
Python functions.
Not too complex.
What are we doing here?
I am creating a function which is
called Calculate expression.
The meaning of this is,
whenever I provide any expression,
let's say 27 into 4 plus 5.
This is an expression.
I want the mathematical calculation
to be done in this function itself.
What am I doing for that?
I am allowing only these numbers and
plus minus addition and subtraction.
And then after that, I am providing
an eval expression.
What this eval does is,
this will calculate the result of
this output.
And it will give you the result.
Very simple.
So this is the very basic function
that we are doing to calculate the
output using an expression like
this.
Mathematical expression.
And after that, to demo or fake the
weather kind of data.
What am I doing here?
I have created one more function
which is called GetWeather.
And it will take the parameter as
city.
Okay.
If we give this city, it should give
us the output of the weather.
So to fake the data, I have created
a dictionary here.
What this is doing is,
it is saying fake weather.
If it is Hyderabad, it is 32 degrees
partly cloudy and humidity is 65
percent.
I am directly providing the output.
Where are you?
You can try to hit the API directly.
But right now, for simplicity
purpose, I am not hitting API for
our learning.
This is the weather in Bangalore.
This is the weather in Mumbai.
This is the weather in Peddapuram.
This is the weather in Chennai and
Delhi.
And whenever you ask for any kind of
city, it is going to return the
weather.
Very simple, right?
So these are the two functions that
we have created.
Basic Python functions.
Let's try to call these two
functions with a simple example.
What are we doing here?
Calculate 25 into 4 plus 100 is the
expression.
And getWeather is Hyderabad.
Let's do this.
So the output came from the first
function.
From this function, we got the
output as 200.
And the output came from the second
function.
Because it is Hyderabad,
we are going to return a similar
output.
But one of the things that we need
to remember is that both of the
functions are returning the output
in the form of string.
So you need the output or return in
string format.
I will help you or I will teach you
in the later part of this video.
But this is very, very important.
Now we have defined the functions,
right?
Now what we need to do is we need to
pass these functions to the LLM.
Now the functions that we have
written, the LLM should know how to
use it and when to use it.
For that, we need to create a JSON
file to describe all of these
functions.
What is our function?
What is our schema?
What are the inputs?
What are the outputs?
All these details.
So this is the JSON file that we
have.
Now what I will do is I will explain
this JSON file more visually in the
notepad.
Now look at this one.
This is our first function,
which is called the Calculate.
And then getWeather.
It is going to take expression as
your input.
And it is going to return you this
output.
And what does this function do?
And then getWeather.
It is going to take city as your
input.
And it is going to return the
weather as an output.
And what this function does?
Now let us define these functions
using a JSON file.
What are we doing here?
You are creating a list of
dictionaries in which our first
function is what is the type.
And that function should be there.
And after that function,
what is the name of that function?
And what does that function do?
Evaluate a mathematical expression
and return the result.
Use this for mathematical
computations.
Here you need to define it using
plain English.
And then what should we do after
that?
What are the parameters of that
function?
What is the parameter type?
It is a string.
It is called an object.
And what are the properties?
It is going to take the expression
as a parameter.
It is going to be a string.
And what is the description of that
string?
You need to give a value there.
And look at this one.
You are giving an example of how
that parameter input should be.
This is basically a one -shot
prompt.
Isn't it?
Remember the prompt engineering
video.
And after that, whether it is a
required function field or not.
It is a required one.
And this is how you will define how
is your first function working in a
JSON schema.
And after that, we have one more
function which is called weather.
Type function.
Function name is weather.
What does this do?
Get current weather city in India.
And what are the parameters?
Object parameter is a city.
This is a string.
That parameter will take whether it
is a required parameter or not.
So, this tool is basically the JSON
schema of all the functions or the
tools that you
have created as a plain Python
functions.
Very simple stuff.
Nothing complex at all.
You need to pass these tools as an
input to the LLM when you provide
your question.
It will think from its knowledge.
And it will decide whether it needs
to call an LLM or a tool.
So, let's look at that one.
Then we need to pass these tools to
LLM.
How do we pass it?
So, let's say this is my message.
We have already set the system
prompt.
What is the question?
What is 1547 x 23 plus 89 and
so on.
Now let's print and execute this
one.
Look here.
We are calling this client.
And specifically, here look at this
one.
This is where you are providing your
tools.
You are providing your tools.
If you look at the output choice,
what is the finish reason?
Tool calls.
Here the finish reason is not the
top.
It is not giving you the direct
answer.
Even though it can give you the
direct answer.
Here our 4 -0 mini NM model is
not directly giving the answer.
Because according to the pattern
description,
whenever we are providing this kind
of question,
it needs to go and act via tools.
Isn't it?
So, look at this one.
Finish reason is a tool call.
And then look at this one.
Role is an assistant.
And then it decided to do this one.
Function is equal to function.
And then it took the arguments.
This is the expression.
15, 47, 23, plus 89.
And name is equal to calculate.
Look at this one.
Then what did the RGBT do?
Based on this question,
without giving the direct answer,
it decided to call this function.
Calculate function.
And from our question,
it is going to extract what is the
expression that you need to pass.
Why?
We have given few shots,
right?
And then it is saying that
I need to call this tool.
And then based on the output from
the tool,
it needs to answer.
So, this is our question.
You are passing it to ChatGPT.
And what did ChatGPT do?
Instead of directly providing the
answer,
it decided to go via a tool.
And this tool is basically
calculated.
After the tool is executed,
it will go back to ChatGPT
and it will give you the answer.
That is how an agent will work,
right?
It will work until
the work has been completed.
Then only it will give you the
answer.
So, by default,
ChatGPT cannot execute this tool.
Because the code written by this
tool
is in your laptop.
And ChatGPT
is sitting at OpenAI servers.
So, it cannot directly execute it.
But let us look at how to execute
this manually first.
So, what are we doing here?
We are just printing all the other
things.
So, the function stopped
because of tool calls.
And it decided to call this tool.
Calculate the arguments
and the tool ID.
And you can do the same thing using
Groq.
You get the same thing even if you
use Groq.
But I am not going to explain the
code for Groq.
What should we do now?
We got a tool call.
But we are not executing that code.
We need to execute it manually.
So, we have the answers from
ChatGPT.
We have this output, right?
So, from this output,
we are going to extract all the
parameters
that we need.
And we are going to call the
function Calculate
and get the output.
So, what are we doing first?
You are going to get this one
from the output we got.
We need to call the function
Calculate.
And then you are going to put this
expression.
And after that,
look at this one.
This is the tool call.
What is it saying here?
It is telling us to call the
function Calculate.
And this is the function name.
And what are these arguments?
This is what this argument is.
And after that,
from the available tools,
we need to call a tool.
You are passing all of these
arguments here.
And you are getting the result.
So, this is basically manually
executing
that tool
on your notebook
based on
the output
of the first
LLM call.
First LLM call.
That's it, right?
We are taking the output we got
and calling the function
from the available tools.
Nothing too complex.
Then we got an output
of 35670.
And we need to provide
this 35670 output
back to charge GPT
such that it can give you the answer
directly.
So, what is happening here?
Again,
you are appending
this is what the initial output is.
Initial output
of charge GPT.
And after that, what did we do here?
We called a tool
and
what is the ID of that tool
and what is the result of that tool.
So, you are appending to all of
these
messages.
It is basically the history
or the tool execution.
And then
you are sending
it to charge GPT again.
Now, charge GPT will summarize
the answer for you and you will get
the final response. So,
let me show you
the flow actually.
So, this will go to charge GPT
first and then charge GPT
decided to go via a tool
call and
what did you do here?
You executed this tool
and whatever the output
that you get,
you send it back to charge GPT.
Now, charge GPT is looking at these
two
results and then it is
giving you a summary of the answer.
What did you do here?
You are executing this manually.
Remember this step.
Now, let us look at the output that
we are going to get
by doing this thing.
So, what did you do here?
You are getting the result of 1547
times 23 plus 89
is 35670.
So, we just created
one single agent
that can do the tool call
of calculating the numbers.
But, where?
We have executed the code
manually by human in the loop.
Now, what we are going to do is
let us keep every single thing
that we have coded so far in a
single cell.
This may seem complex
but it is a very small piece of
code.
What did we do?
What is our message here?
After that, you are calling to a
charge GPT
LLM using the tools.
Whatever the output it gets,
you are extracting the information
which tool to call.
After that, you are putting that
tool
as an execution JC.
Then, you are putting all of the
messages
in the message.append.
Then, you are again calling the
charge GPT
and then you are getting the answer.
This is how a normal
manual flow of an agent would work.
But, what do we want?
We want the agent
to be working autonomously for us.
But, we should not have
to execute the code manually.
So, that is what we are going to do
which is called the
Autonomous Agent Loop.
Now, what we are going to do is
very simple step.
We will put the code
inside a loop.
Very simple.
So, what is the loop?
Until the work is done,
execute the loop
and then you get the output.
Very simple. Nothing too complex.
We will put the same code
inside the function
runAgent.
We are just printing
some extra information that is
needed
for us to debug.
What I am saying here is
to execute the
code
you are hitting the charge GPT.
You will get the output.
From there, the charge GPT
stops directly. It is not
deciding to go via tool calls.
So, then you will stop the execution
here.
If you want to go to tool calls
if you have choice.message.
tool calls, then
you call the tool and then you
put the messages and then you
call the same charge GPT again
and you get the output.
Very simple.
The code we wrote earlier
we just executed every single thing
in a loop and let's execute
this piece of code.
Now, let's look at this scenario.
What should we do?
I want to calculate this output
by saying runAgent.
So, if I execute this piece of code
directly, it will give you the
result.
By saying step 1 and step 2.
Because what does step 1 do?
Based on this question,
it is deciding
whether to call a tool or not.
Simple. In step 2, we got
the final answer.
So, now let's look at the weather
example.
Let's say the weather in Hyderabad
is like this.
Let's execute this.
By saying the weather in Hyderabad
is like this.
So, we got the output result.
Very simple.
Now, let's say what is python?
Now, see
what is python is a general
question.
Now, based on the knowledge of
charge GPT
it can answer directly.
It doesn't need any tools,
right?
Now, based upon the same code
let's see if it decides to go
by a tool or if it doesn't decide to
go by a tool.
So, let's execute this.
So, what is python?
Now, let's look at the output.
Your final answer is ready.
And it didn't go to step 2.
Why? Because it doesn't need
any tool calls.
Based on the knowledge it has
it is providing the answer.
See, what did we do here?
We gave hands and legs to the LLM
GPT.
What did our brain do?
It decides based on
the user's question
when to use hands and when to use
legs
and when not to use hands and legs.
So, based on that
it is giving you the output.
This is what a simple agent is.
Many people
say it is difficult to build agents
and this and that.
Nothing else. This is how you build
a normal python simple agent.
Now, what should we do?
If you want a complex agent
you write complex functions,
complex tools.
Simple.
And if you extend tools
that is what we call it as an MCP.
And if tools have a rag
then rag is an agentic rag.
Very simple stuff guys.
Nothing complex at all.
Now, let's look at this one.
So, what is the weather in
Hyderabad?
It can do a lot of stuff.
So, what we do now is
now that you know every single thing
I will give you how you can
build a basic data analyst agent.
We have data.
If you give questions in that data
it will give you answers.
Simple. Nothing complex.
Now, what will I do?
Let's say this is my data.
I am defining it directly in the
notebook
so that you can easily access it.
And then let me execute this
and I will not explain the code line
by line guys.
What am I doing here?
I am creating some tools or some
functions
basic python functions.
Nothing at all.
Look here.
And then I am printing all of these
things.
And now we need to define the tools
so that
charge GPT or any LLM can use.
So, that is what we are creating
here.
CSV tools and JP.
All the functions we have written
you have already created.
And then we have these questions.
Now, you can directly question.
Here is my data.
Based on this data
I can ask my LLM
to do the data analyst job for me.
So, now look at these questions.
Where are these?
This is our run
CSV analyst function that we have
created.
Everything in a loop.
We will do that. And let's look at
this one.
What is the average salary in the
company?
Now, let's execute and see.
Now, we have taken this tool.
It is calculating our average
salary.
And how many people work
in engineering? Who are they?
What is it doing here?
So, it is doing or using a tool
which is called filter count.
And it is giving you the output.
And after that, which department has
higher
salaries in engineering or
marketing?
So, it is using
get stats, filter count,
filter count, filter count,
multiple
times using the same tool
it couldn't answer
within the step limit.
So, we have seen five times.
Based upon that, it is not answering
it.
So, even the tools have limitations
if you don't
write your tools powerful enough.
That is why I want to show you this
example.
You can solve any problem.
But your tools should
be capable of doing all of that
stuff. So, how many employees are
there
in Hyderabad? Now, let's look at
this one.
Look. It is using two tools.
Filter count and list columns.
This is how you build an agent.
This is how the chart GPT
will do analysis for you.
Someone has already built all of
this.
But, if you are using API,
you need to build all of these
things.
And after that, if you want to
do it in production level,
you need to do multiple retries.
So, what happened here?
We executed it
once and it is not giving us
the answer. Maybe, if we execute it
once more, you might get the answer.
Let's see. Let's execute it once
more.
Now, let's see.
Even it is going a lot of time,
it is not getting the answer.
But, if you execute it
multiple times,
it can give you the answer.
Even if you do it multiple times,
you are not going to be stuck in a
loop.
You need to break the loop.
So, those are
some limitations that you need to
put,
which are called retries,
back off
and hard stops. What is retry?
Try again if it fails.
If it fails the first time,
try again.
What is back off?
Between every retry, maybe wait
10 -15 seconds. Maybe,
it could help.
And, what is hard stop?
After retry 5 times,
let's not retry anything.
It is not going
to answer for us. We are going to
waste
lot of tokens and it is going to
give us a lot of bill.
So, I don't want to do
a lot of infinite number of times
to call the same function.
So, all of these things are very,
very
important and I put the code here
guys. Call LLM with a retry
and run agent with a safe use
and then I can just do it.
That's how you build
an agent from scratch in
Python. Very simple, right?
Now, what will you do?
If you want to build a very powerful
agent, what should you do?
You just create multiple
tools. This is your LLM.
Here, tool 1, tool 2, tool 3,
tool 4, tool 5, tool 6,
tool 7, tool 8.
You can give n
number of tools.
And, you define every tool properly.
Then, the LLM can
choose which tool to use
properly. And, why
should we put starting string output
in functions?
Because,
these LLMs are string models
or text models, right?
If you provide numerical outputs,
it is not
going to understand properly.
That's why, for every tool
we write, you are going to
give the output or written
format in the format of string.
Such that, LLMs can utilize it
much effectively. Here,
in tools, you can put APIs.
You can try, make my trip
API booking. And, then,
you
can also do weather API.
You can also do a lot of stuff.
You can connect to database.
You can connect to your
dashboards. So, this is how you
make powerful LLMs
or powerful agents.
So, let's summarize everything that
we have learned
in this talk. Why do we
need tools? And, what are
JSON schemas? How to execute tools
manually? And, then, message history
and DNT. How to create agent loop?
How to create chile? Provide as well
as swap
chile using
charge GPT and grok. And,
also, safety nets
and DNT and JP. That's it.
And, you will get the whole
notebook in the description below,
guys.
And, if you learned something new
from this video,
comment something
in the video. Because,
I don't
want to be that guy where,
let's
say, comment AI roadmap and
I will give you the notebook.
No, I don't want
to be that guy. And, if you know
someone
who likes this video, please share
it with
them. And, that's all for this
video.
Let's see. Bye -bye.